嗯。
噉啊！
係咪安排緊㗎啦？
好，早晨啊！
救鐘救人，亦都好準時啊！
同埋Amperes嘅行政總監華安啊女士嘅。
噉啊，以及咧西九咧就有佢哋嘅行政總裁啦，柏志高先生啦，啊。
咁而然咧，係新槍同意咧，委員咧可以喺特別會議上面咧，根據該意見書。
誒提出問題嘅，以及透露咧有關提問所依據嘅資料嘅來源嘅，噉啊，大家清楚嗬。
好正，好中意呢個安排。噉啊，好啦，噉就而家可以邀請呢一個政府當局及西九文化管理局嘅代表進入會議室嘅。
管誒西九管理局項目管項目監管總監司徒澤文先生啦，啊諮詢諮詢法律顧問樂基道先生。
噉啊一路入嚟咧，一路介紹啦。今日出席會議嘅啊，包括咧有我哋民政事務局常任秘書長謝玲潔晶女士嘅。噉啊，另外民政事務局工程策劃總監李關兆娟女士啦，土木工程拓展處南拓展處處長彭亞麗女士。
意見書咧，誒，鑑於咧係新窗咧，其實係要求將意見書係保密嘅，委員咧係唔可以向聯合小組嘅委員會以外嘅任何人咧提供或讓其獲取該意見書，誒誒或當中任何嘅部分嘅誒複製本。
好啦，咁多位咧，我哋就可以開會啦。噉啊，開會前咧就同大家講講啦。啱啱大家入嚟嘅時候咧，都應該都係收到啊同事交畀你哋個信封入邊有啲補充嘅資料嘅。噉啊，就住新昌營造廠有限公司咧所提交嘅意。
噉啊！歡迎咁多位代表咧係出席會議嘅。咁喺度咧都提醒啊，西九文化管理局嘅代表咧啊，今日大家係發言咧及所提及交嘅文件咧係均唔會受到《立法會權力及特權條例》嘅保障同埋豁免嘅。
多謝主席。
大家亦都可以先就誒，即係。
And of course, this has implications for both parties going forward.
所以讓我 look at some of the background and a lot of this is set out in the annex one to the paper.
since then， the authority has closely monitored the financial condition of Sinchong Construction.
the board instructed the authorities' management to continue to refine those actions and keep the board briefed on the situation.
The West Kalim Cultural District Authority Board was first briefed on the position in November 2016.
安排同埋決定咧，作詳細嘅解釋。噉我而家就請誒行政總裁柏志高先生以投影片向委員介紹。唔該。好。
I will start by giving a few points, and then I'll pass on to Jeremy to take us through some of the key issues in respect of the construction programme.
First, it is important that I stress that even though the authority has terminated the employment of Sinchon Construction under the contract, the terms of the contract still apply.
at that meeting, the board was advised by management of possible actions open to the authority, in the event that Sinchon Construction were unable to continue with construction of the M+ project under the contract.
今日一啲嘅文件啊，作一啲簡短嘅介紹嘅，而家可以交個時間畀你哋啦。係，誒主席，我首先誒主席早晨，各位議員早晨。我首先做個簡單嘅開場白嚇。
concerns over the financial situation first emerged following publication of an online article by anonymous analytics about Sinchong Construction's parent company, Sinchong Group Holdings Limited, on the 28th of September 2016.
First, I'd like briefly to talk about the process and considerations leading to the decision to terminate the employment of Sinchon Construction Company Limited, and I'll just refer to them as Sinchon Construction from now on, under the M+ Main Works contract with effect from the 17th of August of this year.
誒主席就議員表示關注一有關西九文化區管理局早前向M加工程項目主要承建商新窗營造廠有限公司（簡稱新窗營造）嘅主要分判商直接支付已經核實完成嘅工程費用嘅安排，同埋第二最近八月十七號管理局宣佈終止同新窗。
營造所簽訂嘅M加工程合約嘅事宜咧，表示關注。咁其實呢兩項事件咧，其實個性質咧都係屬於西九文化區管理局嘅誒建造合約管理嘅問題嘅，即係我哋所謂嘅contract management。咁所以我哋今日咧係誒要請到西九文化區嘅管理局咧，就上述嗰兩項。
January of 2018.
和the parent company.
this constituted a cross default.
The direct payments not only bolstered.
on the eighteenth of May, two thousand eighteen.
and given the revelations about the financial state of the Sin Chong Group.
the confidence of their subcontractors, but also ensured that the subcontracted work continued.
The works were at a critical point of construction, with the installation of the five mega trusses underway.
It has also been important to the board that these measures have seen workers being paid on time.
made at the end of September 2016， there was grave concern among their subcontractors about Sinchon Construction's finances.
The board is being kept informed throughout and and has endorsed all of the steps taken to ensure the continuity of the M Plus project.
當的Authority at the request of Sinchon Construction first agreed to make direct payments to Sinchon Construction's subcontractors.
一， of the paper， and this simply sets out the history of the deterioration over the last eighteen months or so.
我 of course refer members to our summary of the available details of the financial position of Sinchon Construction and its parent company, as I say at Annex.
The parent company made an announcement that they could not repay 300 million dollars in senior notes due for redemption on that date.
Indeed, on this point, and to avoid any confusion among members, I made it very clear that the authority was paying the contractor and the subcontractors, not their employees. When specifically asked about reports of late payments to employees or subcontractors, in the finance committee meeting in December 2017 and again in.
on its。
with effect from July 2018.
Following the board meeting on the 28th of June.
新鴻Construction did not respond.
一百五十萬美元，Senior Notes， due in two thousand and nineteen。
and to demonstrate that they have sufficient liquidity to pay their staff and the subcontractors.
and I think it's important to point out that Sinchon Construction is a guarantee to the 2019 notes.
那公眾 announcement 剝除 任何 殘餘 疑問， 作為 而言，新鴻建設 是 insolvent。
和 had resulted in cross defaults under other loan agreements to which the parent company and/or its subsidiaries were parties.
Indeed, a key subcontractor withdrew its staff and ceased work on site due to a failure to pay them.
at the same time, the company was told that the authority considered them to be insolvent, and they were asked to respond.
新鴻的Construction's response to that letter was considered totally unsatisfactory by the third-party administrator.
在July，following the cessation of the direct payment arrangements，Sinchon Construction lost a further two weeks' progress against the revised programme。
成員批准了一個行動計劃，under which the authorities subsequently wrote to Sinchon Construction in June to tell them of the discontinuation of the temporary arrangements of direct payment to subcontractor.
Against that background, on the 16th of August 2018, the authority's management briefed the West Caribbean Cultural District Authority board on the situation, and the board gave approval to terminate the employment of Sinchon Construction under the contract.
of the subcontractors.
under this arrangement, the existing lump sum contractors.
二零一八， to take over the M Plus project through to completion.
for the continuation of the M+ project by way of innovation.
到一 wholly owned subsidiary of the authority，叫Bluepolls Limited。
Program that we briefed members on in November of last year.
sorry lump sum contracts of the subcontractors are transferred to Bluepoles Limited.
但係，它已經被取決於非常謹慎和適當的考慮，和在M+項目的最佳利益。
It is the authority's intention to secure most, but not all, of Sinchon Construction's subcontractors.
We announced the appointment of a management contractor, Gammon Construction Limited, on Friday, September the seventh.
這是一個 wholly owned subsidiary， which was set up to take over such contracts in the event of Sinchong Construction's failure.
With the appointment of the managing contractor and the novation of subcontractors underway, I do believe this is now achievable.
termination of the employment of Sinchong Construction under the terms of the contract has been a very, very difficult decision for the authority to make.
但的 subcontractors work is programmed, organised and supervised by the new management contractor, while they are all paid by Bluepolls Limited.
Having terminated Sinchon Construction's employment under the contract, the authority has now procured a management contractor to complete the remaining construction works.
and I want to give an assurance that we're now focusing on delivering the museum building by the end of 2019, with the opening of the M+ museum in 2020, in accordance with the
also at that time, the third party contract administrator wrote to Sinchon Construction to express their view that Sinchon Construction was not progressing the work with due diligence in accordance with the revised programme, and asked for proposals as to how Sinchon Construction would improve their lack of performance against the programme.
project.
Thank you, Duncan. Good morning, members.
Finally, just an update on where we are in August, which is when the employment was terminated.
I'd like to ask Jeremy to take us through a short presentation to explain some of the technical reasons why, at various stages, we felt it was important to keep the project moving forward. Thank you, Jeremy.
which are supporting the tower above, and then they have three smaller trusses, again which span over the airport railway for the podium deck of the museum.
The temporary steelwork that's supporting those large trusses is finally removed, and what we call the load transfer is then taken down vertically either side of the airport railway.
That's the first major element. Secondly, at the back here, we have a conservation and storage facility, which will house the artwork, and adjacent to that, to the east, is a retail, dining and entertainment building, which is part of the OACF.
And you can see there, it dissects the building almost in half. And the difficult challenge for this building has been building over this airport railway. And this has been achieved by five very large trusses, which you can see there in black lines.
So just to say a few words about where we are with the construction, and also to explain a little bit about the uniqueness and the journey that we've taken with the building so far. Members can see on the screen there. Obviously, this is a pictorial view.
The building that we're delivering, the main M+ museum in the centre there, which is made up of the tower you can see here, which is about 16 floors, and the horizontal podium deck, which is where all the galleries are located.
For the development, just in front of the museum, which you can't see in this picture because it's buried, is an underground car park for about two hundred plus spaces, and also underground is a sewage pump station that we built on behalf of the government. So there's really five elements to this.
So, just really want to touch on three of these today for members: the mega trusses, which CEO referred to in his opening statement, which was a very critical and unique part of this project. Also, the construction of the facade for the building, and then.
So just to look at the mega trusses being a key element of the project, you can see on the screen here, which is a plan view. The green is the the building, and the big yellow stripe going through the the plan there is the airport express tunnels, the MTRC airport express tunnels.
Two at the bottom, two in the middle supporting the tower, and one going north to south. This has enabled the museum podium and the tower to span over the airport railway, and I have a few pictures of that. This is a three-dimensional picture. You can see there, two of the big trusses.
So here's just a pictorial view. This is roughly where we were in around August last year. A lot of this orange or red colour steelwork is temporary. These trusses was suspended off the ground, built sort of bottom up, and you can see here on this picture.
This is when some of the temporary steelwork begins to come down. The airport railway running below these trusses. So you can see there, it's a simple span over the airport railway. But these obviously are very significant trusses. You can see there, this is where we were in around November seventeen, where.
Okay.
Today.
with the main structure.
Again, you can see the main trusses here.
quite significant in height.
You can see there just a aerial view of the tower.
They're a composite structure, which means that they're made of very thick steel plate, which is about 100 mil thick.
And then they're encased in reinforced concrete, and left you know for several days. The welds take three days each.
Made in Europe, we had something like 320,000 tiles that were made in Europe, and then these were shipped to China.
這些樑是非常顯著的，它們約15米深，它們重約1800噸，最重的一個，最輕的一個約860噸。
This is for the tower structure, so you can see there these panels. These are heavy panels, nine or ten tons each. And you can see there, this would be the interior finish on the inside of the of the facade panels.
We have a little video to show. This was taken in about the fourth quarter of two thousand and seventeen. You can see here three of the major trusses that was supporting the two of the big ones supporting the tower there.
And the podium deck, which was not yet complete, you can see here. There's a section on the south side, which was still to be constructed. So at the end of last year, we hadn't actually constructed all of the structure yet of the main museum. Hence, it was at a critical stage of the project.
To to weld, so you can see this was a very significant point of the project in around Q4 2017, and the temporary steelwork below those trusses was removed just early in 18. So this was around eight months ago from where we are.
Okay, so just moving on to item two. The other sort of unique aspect of this building was the construction of the facade. These are the it's a precast concrete facade with a terracotta tile, ceramic tile finish. The tiles were
That's where they were married with the precast structure to form the facade. So a lot of this was made off site. These are mock-ups that we made in two thousand and seventeen off site. You can see there the facade panels as a mock-up with the.
We also do.
和的panels that are put into place.
again, this was at the end of last year.
在實際 permanent 位置 on the tower.
And I think we have a video here which just shows.
What you're seeing on the video there is the tower facade.
tests for the gondola which
shows some of them being erected on the on the main tower.
So where are we today with the construction progress?
That's a picture on the south side. You can see there. This was taken in around June of two thousand and eighteen.
How the panels are lifted into place. Again, this is on the mock-up, and we have a slide showing it happening on the on the actual project.
The CSF building, which I mentioned earlier, we're about eighty percent of the structure completed, and the retail dining and entertainment building to the east is around fifty-two percent.
This is a mock-up that we made off-site in China. Quality-wise, we do a lot of testing for the podium and the tower facade. This is a water test you can see there to ensure that there's no leakage, or if there is any leakage, you can see here.
So you can see here, we do very intense quality tests where water is sprayed intensely against the facade, so we can check for any leakage with the joints. And this is all done before the panels are shipped to site and installed.
is for cleaning the facade of the tower, and we also check that that you know if that knocks against the main facade that there's no quality issues with the with the tiles. So you can see here, these are some of the facade panels being delivered to site, and this picture.
Forgive me for the fair bit of text on this slide, but you can see there with the with the main tower, we've almost top tail. We're about ninety five, ninety to ninety five percent constructed. The podium is around ninety percent constructed as as regards the RC concrete.
喺個video。
to complete where we are.
on the east to complete.
And you can just see the the top of the tower here.
The tower facade panels, we've installed around 24%.
And the right one is the retail dining, entertainment block, which has progressed.
And as I mentioned, the interfacing car park underneath the car underneath the park is almost completed at 94%.
所以，The work to progress from here is really a lot of the fit out, and a lot of the mechanical and electrical planning.
The pump station for government is practically practically complete, and there's some external works that have progressed around thirty five percent.
The buildings at the rear, which I mentioned, the RDE and the conservation storage facility. Again, that building almost having topped out.
just a couple of pictures of the facade that was taken in sort of early August, so you can see the south face there and the north face there was sort of almost halfway up.
And then the last few there relate to the finishing inside the building, which is still to do, only around 10%. The mechanical, electrical and plumbing around 25%.
The podium deck here, you can see one of the tail cranes in the middle there being dismantled. This hole needs to be filled in, but the main structure of the museum is already formed.
The video there shows the car park, which is underneath this area here, which will be covered by the park. And as I said earlier, that's about ninety-five per cent completed.
So just a few final pictures. That is looking from east in a westerly direction. You can see the Western Harbour Tunnel there in the background. So the tower is almost topped out on the west, and there's a small portion.
So this is a video taken in around August, just to show the construction. You can see there, this is moving from south to north. The tower has almost topped out. These two buildings at the back, the left one is the conservation and storage facility.
好。
噉啊！
係，多謝主席。
So, thank you, Chairman. Happy to answer any questions.
誒局方同西九都介紹曬咯，係嘛？
每位委員咧，連問連答咧就。
We have around 86% of the tower structure completed.
咁如果係咁咧，我就而家喺可以誒邀請委員提問啦。噉啊～
You can see there. This is in the RDE building, and also the RDE building on the left there.
And eighty percent of the CSF building also completed by August.
We have around 85% of the horizontal podium structure completed.
噉啊，松裕啲啦，我哋都係睇咁多人呢度，就五分鐘，五分鐘好嘛？咁首先咧就係謝偉全議員。
And then finally, the RDE building, which is 16 floors, we're about halfway up on the structure.
And you can see here, we've also installed some of the mechanical, electrical, plumbing in the building, also.
So just to reconfirm, as of August, just before termination, about 94% of the basement structure is complete.
誒當然咧，就就呢個誒Amphas博物館嗰個工程方面咧，世界管理局啊，即係最近採取嘅各方面嘅做法咧，其實我或者好多人都關注其中咧，當然係考慮咧，就係關於嗰個工程嘅進。
The.
situation.
As a listed company to the stock exchange.
嘅係咪穩健？咁呢個第一點咧，就誒，我想。
和 consequent implications of those announcements on Sinchon Construction.
The situation of the parent company Sinchon Group is a factor, in so far as our determination of Sinchon Constructions.
第二個 issue that is of concern to us is the progress on the site and whether that was due to financial situation or management incompetence or what other reasons.
The basic situation, as as described in Annex One of the paper, really flows from announcements made by Sinchon Group.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Let me deal with the the issue insolvency. Our relationship is only with Sinchong Construction. We have no direct relationship with Sinchong Group. However, of course.
It's very clear from the information we've provided in the paper that the core at the heart of the issues relating to delays is the financial situation.
講嚴咧，即係可能係因為好多因素。咁呢個因素咧，係唔係誒有冇去評估一下咧？係咪完全係新窗嘅責任咧？誒，先問呢兩個問題。唔該，主席。好，管理局。
個關係係點樣？同埋誒喺呢個佢哋嗰個財政穩健，或者係承擔嗰個有關工程，你哋係滿意佢嘅財政方面嘅誒各方面咧個關係係點咧？我想第一瞭解呢樣嘢。
度同埋個工程嘅造價，另外當然咧，即係合同方面咧，可能涉及好複雜啊。好似柏志高講，即係採取最後咧，就係取代咗嗰個新昌作為呢個總承建商方面嘅決定。
噉啊，就呢幾個問題咧，我想即係有幾個問題可以誒跟進一下問下。第一，即係喺誒呢個一五年咧，決定啊將呢個工程判畀新昌嘅時候咧，我相信誒西九管理局咧會考慮過咧新昌嗰個財政。
瞭解一下，因為而家似乎咧就係一年多之後咧，新昌嗰個誒集團啊，即係佢嗰個誒新昌集團嘅控股有限公司咧，似乎係可能喺財政方面咧出現啲問題，但係同呢個成商新昌營造方面咧。
第二咧就係誒關於嗰個誒成個工程咧，當然而家咧出現咗嗰個延誤嘅問題。噉啊延誤咧，主席大概我我我同文件所知咧，就係應該有三百四十幾日啦，即係而家嚟講。咁呢個延誤咧係一般工程嚟。
insolvency issue.
Okay, thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Are you a liar?
誒，Access go to the CEO。
睇下可唔可以直接啲答四位議員啦。
主席，或者我第二次跟進。好，誒。
我就後啲先啦，譚文豪議員。
And have continued up to date. I'm hoping that with the appointment of the new
係唔係即係評估個係新窗，完全係新窗嘅責任？誒，麥志高先生噉啊。
Mr. Chairman, the relationship is that HCC is obviously a subsidiary of HCG.
That was the reason that we, with the board support, stood in and paid direct to the subcontractors. That has allowed the project to continue.
But of course, as we announced in November of last year in our regular report to members, the the implication of the delays were quite substantial even then.
你嗰個付款理約保函嗰方面咧，同嗰個誒呢個新昌集團個關係點啊？我我唔明啊，即係因為計即係一間公司雖然可能一個集團，但係個影響係點樣？第一點我睇唔到。第二樣我想問嗰個疑問咧。
主席啊，可唔可以直接咧？即係雖然五分鐘咧，我想答答個問題，嗰個關係頭先話係阿柏志高先生話嗰個因素咧，即係總公司個即係嗰個新昌集團咧。但係我睇係咪可以講下即係佢個承諾？因為你咀照咧嗰個新昌營造咧。
That's correct.
On。
我申請。
And you said.
The financial state.
Number one.
Number two, I'm sorry.
The financial.
Let's look at some facts before we draw a conclusion.
According to the appendix.
Right. However, if you look at your appendix one.
Finance Committee on the end of last year.
I specifically ask you, what is
I can certainly confirm that, as far as our tracking is concerned, all the workers are being paid on time.
Do you want me to answer that? Yes. Well, the simple answer is no, of course. Okay. Did you mislead this council? Of course not. Okay. Good.
the the relationship is one such that when you investigate HCC as we did back in two thousand and fifteen before the appointment, we did look into the parent company. There was no indication at that stage that there were any financial issues, and as I indicated, it emerged subsequently.
In terms of the the cause for the delay, I think that the cause primarily is due to financial situations. But there are other elements. As I say, this is not a black and white situation. With any construction project, there are many factors that come into play. But the determining factor for us is the.
was it correct?
所以， during that time.
and suppliers in a timely manner.
this adversely impact the progress of the project.
At port number four and five.
And XCC had failed to pay its subcontractors.
Sun Chang has failed to pay his subcontractor.
所以那係一個 delay。
As I say, they were paying them late. No, was it correct? As I say, they were paying them late.
Despite payments made by WKCDA to HCC, which is Centene.
所以， in late two thousand sixteen, WKCDA were concerned that this build.
我唔 have a relationship with the workers. I made that very, very clear. No, that's not my question. My question is back to back to Annex One, number four and number five.
睇下啲轉錄，就係好明顯，你試圖隱藏問題。主席，正如我所説，我當然不會對上市公司嘅財務穩定性發表意見。
Following page, let me quote, Mr. Chairman. I would certainly never comment on the financial stability of a listed company. All I can say is that, as far as I'm concerned, the payments are going out to the contractors and the subcontractors, and they are being paid to the workers.
listed company.
this amendment。
any of this, none of this.
of the payment, of the schedule payment.
Why did you mention any of that? Sorry, I answered your question.
Okay，HCC is not a listed company.
所以，why did you didn't mention any of?
And you mention nothing about all this.
on both occasions, both in December and in January.
In any of the payment, and you say it's all on time. No, I did not.
You did not answer the question. Yes, I did. If you want to read the question, it's all attached as the second annex.
We ask you during the financial meeting. I specifically ask you, okay, is there any delay?
那係我有包括。我嘅問題係唔係只係關於工資，我嘅問題係亦都係關於財務狀況。佢哋係咪喺一個健康嘅狀態？
As I said, I made it very clear that we had taken over the direct payment for wages, and that your question was in respect of the payment to workers, and I answered those questions.
Well, so why in the council, during the council, you say everything's on time? I didn't say everything was on time. I've never said everything's on time. You asked a question specifically about payments. I specifically answered those questions. And indeed, if you refer to the
作為成員們非常清楚，有合約義務，也有交換規則，禁止我對上市公司財務狀況發表意見。我根本沒有資格發表意見，正如你們所説。
They're paying late, exactly. So their payment's late. So why didn't you say it during the financial meeting? Because you asked me a question about the employment. I also asked you what is their financial state, and I said I would not comment on their financial state. Well, you did comment, but you tried to misleading. I did not. I made it very clear. Let me. You did not make it clear. If you look.
However, the parent company is a listed company, and I'm constrained by that fact. Well, again, again, you just answered the other member's question and saying okay, which is not a listed company, okay. Sorry, and now you say it is a, it is not a listed company. Sorry, I did not comment at all on HCC. I made the point HCG is a
譬如話。
新窗就提到咧。
譬如話咧，喺呢個誒。
噉啊，下位啦，朱海迪議員。
有好多嘅。
activated，所以 therefore， it was irrelevant to the council at that stage.
政府都冇嘅，冇嘅係。政府同西九都冇嗰封信嘅，係我哋委員先有嘅啫。
兩方面嘅提問嘅，咁首先我想問下政府係咪都有誒新窗嗰封信嘅，主席？
係誒唔該主席，噉就誒喺誒尋日同埋今朝都收到誒新槍。
誒謬誤嘅原因咧，都係誒西九管理局誒造成嘅。
誒嘅誒一封信啦，咁嗰封信就係唔公開畀公眾嘅。不過我我睇翻誒秘書畀我哋嗰個。
噉我就誒，噉我就根據嗰封信就提出誒兩個具體嘅提問啦嚇。第一個咧就係誒。
And including you form a new company of a BPL, you didn't even mention any of those. Of course not. Those are don't you think that's important to this council?
誒文件咧就話可以根據嗰個意見書誒提出提問嘅，噉我就想根據嗰個意見書去提出誒。
地盤嘅地下水咧，係誒佢嘅水平咧係遠高於誒佢原本誒諗住嘅情況啦。
I always answer members' questions. Now, don't you think that it's important to this council to disclose your change of the payment schedule and also you form a new company of BPL? As far as I'm concerned, the formation of the company was a precautionary matter, and until it was necessary, wasn't it?
但係咧就。
設計上面嘅唔相容嘅。
佢哋嘅誒電腦。
西九管理局就一次都冇批准過。
而呢啲都係誒造成咗誒。
咁咧就誒新窗咧亦都係誒要求。
Mr. Chairman, it's very difficult for me to comment on a on a letter that I haven't seen.
誒新窗就提出咧，係西九管理局咧有誒非法噉樣去入侵。
咁呢個係第一方面嘅誒問題啦。第二方面咧，就有一個指控都幾嚴重嘅，主席就係嗯。
而咧誒喺個過程當中咧，亦都有好多誒需要重新向呢個屋宇署嘅入職。
咁咧誒，另外咧都誒有提到咧，係誒好多嘅設計嘅改動咧，都係由誒西九管理局去提出。
所以，我唔諗我真係可以comment in specifics。what I can say some general points。哦，你可以就住朱海迪議員嘅提問可以回應佢。雖然你冇睇嗰封信。
要求過西九管理局咧係立即停止誒呢種行為，但係咧管理局係拒絕咁做嘅。咁呢兩方面可以請佢回應下先。好誒，Mr. Duncan。
新窗認為咧嗰個延誤嘅好主要嘅原因，所以佢哋認為咧嗰個延誤嘅主要責任咧唔係喺佢哋身上，而係喺西九管理局呢一方。但係咧誒，佢哋就提出咧多次係誒向西九管理局咧要求延期。
喺誒工地裏面嘅電腦咧，噉就去攞誒一啲誒關於個項目嘅資料啦，同埋關於咧誒新窗嘅誒工作人員嘅個人資料，包括身份證啊、護照啊、呢個醫療報告啊。
好。
按個合約。
Various reasons.
under contract.
啊，Patrick先生。
claims for delay for.
Let me talk about some some generalities here.
those are resolved by the independent contract administrator.
好話呢個誒，你你係有權去hack人啲電腦嘅。
As I'm sure there would have been, although I don't know what the exact details are in this case.
There is always a provision for the contractor to submit.
Mr. Chairman, as I say, I don't think I want to comment on a letter I haven't had the benefit of seeing.
我我 can comment in general terms. I'm not talking about specifics. That would be totally inappropriate, given that I don't know what is in the letter.
They go to the contract administrator. They assess them. They come up with a resolution. That's the way it works. So it's not. It's not. Doesn't involve the authority because it's set up under the contract to be dealt with in that way.
As far as allegations about actions that we've taken, of course, I'm not going to respond to those. I will say that that all we have done is under the terms of the contract, we have moved in, we have seized all items of equipment that are in the site, the site officers, and that's provided for under the contract.
嗯。
難。
嗯，你真誠。
啊，彼得先生。
係一個係limited company，我嘅理解有冇錯啊？
都係limited by guarantee嘅，係咪即係我個人係嘛？
唔係，係即係普通嘅一個limited company，即係有限公司，係咪啊？
九管理局核下成立嘅第一間係有限公司咧。
This one is a company set up by shares. The other companies are limited by guarantee.
Mr. Chairman, we we've set up a number of companies. Each one is set up for the particular purpose. This one was set up as by share rather than by guarantee. Yes.
第二咧就係話誒有有好多咧係唔同嘅誒項目裡面之間嘅嗰啲設計嘅唔相容嘅地方，咁咧喺誒信中咧就提到咧係有超過誒十八萬項呢一個誒設。
誒陳淑莊副主席，好多謝主席。誒都有幾個問題嘅噉啊。首先咧，誒我想問一誒先問關於呢一個誒blue post limited嘅咁咧就誒頭先啊，柏志高先生答譚文豪議員嘅時候咧，就話呢一個係即係誒誒以防不備之需，即即即。
即係睇即係不時之需啦。噉我就想問下咧，誒西九管理局喺過往咧有冇誒組過即係組成過或者成立過一啲係唔係limited by guarantee嘅公司？因為咧嗱，我而家手上咧就做咗個查察嘅，就係blue post嘅。咁咧就佢應該係。
而喺西九之下成立以下，即係因為佢哋以前都有成立過一啲公司啦。譬如話係睇Amplas啊，或者甚至係睇誒誒，可能之後誒我哋嘅故宮博物館啊，如果冇記錯嘅話，係咪嗰啲都係即係而家呢一間Blue Post係咪第一間喺西？
我我我問緊係咪第一間係係有限公司形式成立，唔係limited by guarantee嚇，即係唔係嚇？我只係問咁簡單啫，搞兩分鐘都未答到啊！我直接啲咧，咪同埋咧，係啦，我今日都見到個資深誒誒法律顧問喺度。
到啦。另外咧，呢一個咧，我另外睇得到咧。誒，呢一個blue post limited咧，都有個debenture咧，係誒，即係同呢一個西九管理局簽。我都想了解下當中嗰個關係，因為咧而家blue post limited咧就係同緊嗰啲subcontractors嗰啲分判商咧，就開始處理一啲合約嘅。噉我就想誒瞭解一。
誒而家喺呢一個amplus嗰度，究竟有幾多個分判商咧？因為由阿司徒先生口中講過，或者誒喺西九管理局出過嘅誒一啲誒新聞稿咧，誒有十四、十五或者唔同嘅數目嘅。噉我就想知道一有幾多個分判商？二而家呢間blue。
Post Company Limited咧，誒同咗幾多個分派商處理咗佢哋嘅誒分派合約啦。誒同埋三誒誒，即係呢一間Blue Post Limited同西九管理局嘅呢一個Debenture究竟有啲咩關係？因為呢一個Blue Post Limited咧，佢主要係呢個五嗰個資本咧係得五萬蚊嘅啫嚇，即係我都想誒詳細。
In the event.
terms of the。
所以，那它會被。
The nature of the companies.
An ordinary company limited by by shares.
loopholes limited was set up very quickly.
Blue poles had to be deployed to.
And we chose, for that reason, is to set up a.
The debenture was taken out because it was recognised that.
and setting out the the functional sort of nature of the company and what it's there for.
readily available in the event of a failure of the the main contractor.
瞭解一下嗰個誒嗰個成立同埋嗰相關嘅關係，唔該曬。阿朱家老先生。
The first two or three subsidiaries that we set up were companies limited by guarantee.
That takes quite a bit of time because of the the extra details that have to go into the articles of association.
We would not novate for other reasons, but obviously that's it. So we're looking at approximately 15 that we've already been able to novate, and there are a few more that we're still working on. So Mike, if you could answer the legal questions.
嗯。
今日。
誒第一輪就到我啦。
我一間再追問主席。
accept the subcontracts.
That a large amount of money.
咁咧，我就都想一問，即係西九管理局嘅。
係幫佢哋頂咗十八個月。
which would flow from termination of the main contractor's employment under the contract.
所以，那The Authority會有The First Priority， in in the event that there was any issue with blue poles.
噉啊，事實上咧，管理局喺處理今次嘅事件裏面咧，係比誒公眾，包括我自己咧，都覺得係透明度不足嘅。
would eventually flow through, and that would be public money that would flow through blue poles, and to an extent there would be.
係得幾成係唔得咧？因為即係我點解咁講咧？就當咪最可能，似乎公眾認為最艱難嘅時候，係佢啊提出要求幫佢直接畀分判傷嘅時候，你哋居然可以。
some assets of that of that company that needed to be protected, so that we took out a debenture over the shares and the assets of Blue Poles to be held by the authority.
Just to answer the the subcontractors, there's roughly 30 total, of which 14 or 15 are main subcontractors that are quite what we would regard as key subcontractors for the completion of the project. Some of the subcontractors, essentially their work is already completed, so there would be no need to nivate them. Some of
咁而對新窗營造嗰個態度咧，好似都比較飄忽，一時一樣有啲即係唔同嘅轉變噉樣啊！咁所以我係其實好質疑咧，其實管理局咧係對新窗營造嗰個財務狀況咧，究竟係有幾深入嘅瞭解，同埋你憑呢去判決佢喂究竟財務係幾？
under。
situation in Hong Kong.
還是其他原因咧？咁最後啦，就係。
made it very clear that debt was due, it could not be paid.
Clearly, the announcement on the eighteenth of May.
Mr. Chairman, yeah, let me deal with those in order.
一公司係considered to be insolvent if it's unable to pay its debts when they become due. It's as simple as that.
應該都要交代畀我哋聽啦。咁所以我想睇下你哋嘅追討個損失嗰度咧，係做咗啲咩工作嘅？三個問題。
業務公司係有好龐大、具有資源嘅香港承建商，係共同完成呢個Empress工程嘅興建嘅。
咁呢樣嘢其實係點樣？佢判斷佢嘅財務係掂定唔掂嘅咧？呢個係我相信係大眾好關注嘅問題，係咪喺裡面有人失職，係判斷錯誤咧？呢個第一點嘅。
復正常嘅時候咧，喺一個月之後咧，你哋突然間喂就啊話喂唔得喎，佢嘅財務狀況唔掂咯，咁可能要同佢哋係即係喺合約之下咧，係解除啊佢哋嘅角色。
誒，我哋理解到咧，亦都有媒體報道過咧，就其實誒管理局喺同新昌營造解約之後咧，其實自函個呢一個工程合約嘅擔保人美亞保險。
一年半咁長嘅時間，都係覺得冇問題嘅。到跟住媒體報咗光之後，爆咗出嚟之後，噉你哋就話：，誒，啊，我哋會檢討。跟住你哋七月嘅時候出嚟講：，誒，啊，呢一個特殊嘅安排咧，就會檢討啦。咁亦都會好快恢復翻做正常。咁當大家以為一切都係恢
第二點就係嗱，佢咧係財務有問題，咁但係我睇翻佢畀我哋嘅信裏面都有講到咧，其實喺最後尾喺你哋同佢提出解約之前咧，係幾個禮拜之前啦，其實佢都提出過咧係一啲嘅建議，表示咧會同一間可能佢某公司啦，佢。
咁似乎都係提出咗一個喺啊財務上可以分擔，或者係即係畀到大家信心一個可能嘅建議啦。咁但係佢就話咧，最後尾呢個建議咧係畀管理局拒絕嘅。噉我亦都想了解點解你哋會拒絕呢個建議咧？咁即係其實你最主要同佢哋，假如都係因為個財政上面問題，定係？
香港嘅母公司美國國際集團要求對方繳付二點九七億元嘅工程擔保金嘅。我想即係睇下管理局能唔能夠透露更多畀公眾知道，即係喂而家個追討嘅財情究竟係點樣咧？咁另外除咗追討美亞之外咧，合。
約中亦都有冇條款咧，係向新窗係佢追討咧，因為你今次重新嘅招標，可能引致更多嘅開支，誒或者係會令到個工程嘅延期係即係更加深嘅，噉係會涉及到今日即係唔知方方面面，即係。
嗯。
We were getting.
那 was the trigger.
因為up until up until that point.
In the event of a problem with the contract.
好，你繼唔繼續講埋嗰個追討嘅情況係點啊？而家？
所以，The issue is very simple. Could they pay their debt? The answer is no.
我我第二輪先再問啦。誒，周鼎議員第一輪嘅。
Obviously, in this case, insolvency is a major problem with the contract. We called the bond, as we're entitled to do.
not only could they not pay that debt, but it became very clear when we stopped the direct payment.
Yeah, the bond under the terms of the contract. In fact, all of our contracts, we require a bond payable to us on demand.
That has not yet been paid out, and we have issued a writ to the bondholder to require them to pay, and that is now in the court. So I can't really say very much about that.
under instruction from the board, they were not able to pay their subcontractors again. Failure to pay a debt when it becomes due, so the issue of insolvency is very simple.噉你之前又肯幫佢頂十八個月嘅？
Advice and as you can see from Annex One of the paper, they were making statements to the stock exchange to the effect that there were other companies prepared to come in, but in over those 18 months, none of those statements were actually transformed into reality.
It was until they became clearly insolvent that we could take action. But prior to that, of course, we want to try to ensure that we listen to the company. We want to believe them when they say, yes, someone's going to put 300 million, 600 million, whatever the amount is, into the company. Never happened.
Their debt.
issue to build over railways.
The third point is that.
to scrutiny not not just by our advisers but obviously by the board.
但我 can say that every action we have taken has been subject
until it became very evident when they made a statement that they could not pay.
咁要直至到十八月個月嘅之後嘅某一日咧，你先可以達到一個結論，就係話咧佢嗰個財務狀況係唔得，而最後咧導致咧係啊，即係終止個合約嘅決定。
唔該啊，主席。啊，今次嘅事咧就睇到嗰個透明度係好不足嘅。誒，我就想追問一樣嘢咧。正如頭先啊，主席都講咗啦，即係有十八個月嘅時間，其實你係一路幫緊佢哋去畀錢嗰個分半上。
第二點，我 want to make is that the trigger for us to start the direct payments was a request from Sinchong Construction to us to the effect that they indicated that they were struggling to pay, and we had noticed late payments to subcontractors.
prior to that, we had no basis to come to the conclusion that they were insolvent, even though we suspected that that was the case. Hence, we wrote to them to make that point to them and to ask for them to come back and explain whether or not they were. They did not respond, as I indicated in my opening remarks.
啊！呢一個嘅講法咧，可能即係好多嘅公眾咧聽落都仲係有啲質疑嘅，因為事實上有十八個月，你哋的而且確，如果唔係因為啊，佢哋畀唔到錢或者畀唔到錢個分判商，又點會去作為一個措施？你話臨。
臨時又好，或者當下要即刻解決都好，就由你哋去取代佢哋嘅角色，佢直接畀錢個分半商啦。咁呢個其實都係一個好清晰嘅結論，睇到佢的而且確係有個財務問題。咁誒，十八個月嘅時間，我就想問一樣嘢啦。其實你哋我知道可能。
政府有好多時咧做所有嘅決定咧，佢有機會去攞一啲啊外面嘅顧問嘅意見嘅。我請你哋可唔可以解釋一下？其實呢十八個月嘅過程裏面，你哋一路係畀緊錢嗰啲分判商，你哋幾時係攞到嗰啲一啲外面有冇攞到一啲顧問嘅？
意見話畀你聽，喂，唔得啦，係認真，真係要斬攬啦。呢個顧問嘅意見係幾時攞到，或者個詳細嘅內容如果有嘅，能唔能夠都同我哋透露咧？嚇噉，因為好老實講，呢個的而且確咧，我覺得公眾係想知道，特別係要防預防呢啲情況。
當將來會再有機會發生，而家公眾有啲觀感咧，就係其實好似拖咗十八個月，根本就其實應該可能早啲斬攬添嘅。不過就可能而家就冇咁做到噉，所以我都想問下，究竟你哋有冇攞過一啲外來嘅意見或者顧問嘅專業嘅意見？呢啲意見究竟嘅內容係點？可唔可以話畀我？
contract administrator。
We felt it was appropriate for us to give.
歷史會 show， it has enabled us to keep the project moving forward， but there comes a point。
as far as we were concerned, we we back eighteen months earlier had concerns.
所以那係我哋嘅邏輯。Throughout， we wanted to keep the project going， and as you can see， we managed to do that.
要對，任何組織，要告訴另一個組織他們 insolvent，你唔會輕易做呢個。
confidence to the subcontractors that they would get their money, because it was coming from us. Why should it be that they would be paid late?
你唔做喺個 whim，你 have to be certain，因為有咁多 legal and 其他 complications that arise from that。
where it is no longer feasible for us to be doing that if we believe that the company is insolvent, and that's what we believe. Hence, the action we've taken on the 17th of August.
Every payment had to be submitted by Sim Chong. In other words, they also had to certify that the work was done, and then we paid out. So all the payments were for work done, and I believe.
We were not in a position unilaterally to take a view as to insolvency, because the definition, as I as I've indicated earlier, is a straightforward: can you pay your debt or not? Now, up until that point, they were paying but late.
但 at the same time we wanted to ensure that we were not paying more than was actually than the work that was actually being produced on the site, so every payment was certified by the independent
嚟聽係咩情況啊？唔該，畢志高先生。Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yes, with effect from October 2016, we sought both legal and financial advice from external advisers. They've been engaged throughout, and of course, are not at liberty to reveal their advice.
We believe that our our payments to subcontractors was appropriate to ensure that the construction continued at a very critical point when we were putting the trusses in, when we were dealing with issues relating to the the railways. As I'm sure members are away aware, it's a very difficult.
啊，主席，我有一句追問嘅。嗯，如果按照佢頭先呢個結論嘅講法咧，我覺得件事令到管理局都好被動，因為佢嘅講法就話你一定要好似係要等到嗰間公司自己make statement去承認咗佢係insolvent嗰個證據，先可以導致到佢做呢個噉嘅決定。但如果嗰間
間公司一路用各種嘅手段拖住、瞞住，一路都唔搣呢個statement，假時間咁講咧，你就會好被動，不斷咁去用嗰啲所謂臨時方式去幫佢畀錢啊，幫佢頂啊噉樣。其實噉樣對公眾嚟講，其實唔係好公道嘅。你而家好彩係佢搣咗個statement。如果你調翻轉頭咁講，你可以因為佢好彩搣。
個statement畀你而家發現啦，噉佢先你先至有辦法去終止合約。即係我覺得噉樣，如果佢呢個解釋其實係政府變得或者管理局會變得好被動咯。啊，好唔該。Mr. Chairman，I do need to respond to that point. The board were not passive. Um, it is a very difficult thing.
但係，The removal of any residual doubt was the statement made in May 2018. Up until that point, the promises that were being made, the assurances that we were given, we had to accept them at face value. But at that point, we knew exactly what the situation was. So this was not a matter of waiting; it was a matter of certainty.
好。
新鴻group。
誒，謝偉全議員，第二輪。
五咧，如果係新窗嘅責任。
and I think it was appropriate to be certain before we made a difficult decision like this.
但 of course，once it became clear that Sinchon Construction was a guarantor。
They have no role directly in this contract. Our contract is with Sinchong Construction.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'll ask I'll ask Jeremy to comment on the contract management arrangements. I mean, make two points about this.
咁當然啦，佢哋要負責。咁如果唔係咧，其實呢方面咧都可能係有誒呢個索償嘅方面嘅出現嘅。唔該，主席。
營造方面嘅索償喺呢方面嚟講咧，我非常關注，即係呢方面嘅問題。咁所以咧，我首先就話，即係想了解新窗個營造個母公司咧。
好噉啊，柏志高先生，我諗你睇翻即係委員，即係都係繼續問緊嗰個解除合約嗰度咧。咁似乎即係你過去嘅解釋咧，即係頭先都好似未可以講到啲要點，令到大家信服嘅。噉我都想再畀時間你講講。
我諗第二輪都係維持翻五分鐘都冇問題，係係多謝主席嘅。其實我咧就想跟進，頭先我問題嘅，因為其實要終止一個誒承建商嘅合同咧，其實會有非常複雜嗰啲誒合同方面嘅。
權責問題啊，同埋亦都可能即係對嗰個整個工程咧，嗰個造價同埋嗰個時間造成影響。咁當然咧，要作出啲決定咧係艱難嘅。就係呢樣嘢，我想誒即係瞭解清楚一點，因為將來可能面對新窗方面，新窗型。
喺誒呢個合同裏邊咧，佢個關係係乜嘢？同新昌營造呢個第一點，因為喺一五年去平核新昌營造嗰個財政穩健方面咧，新昌冇公司喺合同方面個角色係乜嘢？尤其是咧，我睇到文件第十七段。
咧，似乎都有提過呢樣物。噉，我想希望咧，就係西九管理局或者政府方面喺呢度咧，係可以清楚啊，同我哋講。第二點，啊，我相信咧，即係嗰個疑誤咧，頭先講啦，誒，可能工程嘅疑誤係好多因素嘅。咁呢啲因素。
咧係我相信，誒作為一個管理呢個合同方面咧，西九應該係會去評估一下嚇，即係嗰個責任問題。咁當然我唔知道而家有冇作出評估。如果冇幾時作出評估，因為呢個而。
from the Sinchong Group, that's.
was in con was.
liability for Sinchon Construction.
The defect liability period.
到 certain debt that.
在terms of the delays， yes， of course。
Wrapped up in the final resolution at the end of the.
一個relationship between the two parties. We're not party to that, but it became a determining factor.
the responsibility of Sinchon Group, that became a relevant issue to our determination of their insolvency. And as I said in I think it's paragraph 17 of the paper, that statement came out on May 18th, and therefore it became.
I think it's also important to point out around 80% of the works was subcontracted out to all of the subcontractors that we've been referring to previously, and yes, they they also have claims from the subcontractors up to Sinchong.
In this case, I must point out that we are in dispute with the company. They have announced that we are in dispute. So obviously, all of these issues will be dealt with through the dispute resolution mechanism provided for under the contract. So, Jeremy, if you deal with the the issue of contract management.
As I'm sure the honourable member is aware, there are always claims during the course of a contract. That happens from almost day one, and those claims are assessed, they're determined, and often they're resolved during the the period of the contract. However, some claims are never resolved until the end, and they're
Yes, just to enhance that. Really, I think it's important to point out that we do have this independent contract administrator who looks after the contract side of the project. Whilst we're in dialogue with them under the contract, it is the contract administrator that is in charge of.
Managing the contract, as Duncan has mentioned, throughout that period, we receive notices of delay, claims, and they are dealt with just as normal on all of our contracts, and there's no difference with the M+ situation.
Now that we will be novating a number of these subcontractors to blue poles, and they will be managed by our new contractor. All of the existing terms of those contracts that those subcontractors had will transfer.
Transfer over, and so yes, we still have a period of time where we have to deal with claims from subcontractors, and that will that'll be done in the normal process of dealing with the claims. What we're trying to do is obviously get these subcontractors restarted under our new management contractor, and that's.
唔該，主席。
可唔可以提到出嚟咧？呢啲？
That's our intent at the moment.
之後咧就誒C.O.
One, and working backwards in a sense.
好，譚文浩議員。
their own staff, some wages I think for up to three months.
啊！喺附件二啦，都係翻翻去好冇咁咧。就關於誒財務委員會十二月八號二零一七年嘅時候咧。
Mr. Chairman, the best thing I can do is point you to Annex One, which sets out in great detail various examples. But I can perhaps summarise one or two.
喺第一段已經講咗㗎啦，我就係問你點樣確保呢一個嘅contractor咧係可以財政健康噉樣嚟到完成工程？
就咁答嘅係嘛？Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yes, indeed. That is in fact one of the most important aspects of the contract management that we have. We have a system of independent contract management.
係咧，覺得佢嗰個財政上係出現依方面嘅問題咧，即係如果有呢啲表啊，或者嗰啲誒事態事件咧，我諗我哋更加會有信心，即係個做法啱。
主席，我諗即係我或者有啲人議員都都想知，因為新昌營造咧主要中止佢咧，就因為個財政有問題。咁其實我哋都想知道咧，或者啊柏志高先生可以畀一啲實例咧。過去一段時間，因為頭先李主席都講啦，同佢畀咗錢咧，即係一段時間。咁究竟係有咩實例？
One of the most telling instances was the fact that in July, one of the subcontractors withdrew staff from the site because of failure to pay fees that were due to it. Another instance that has emerged subsequently, which we were obviously concerned about, was failure to pay some of the the
There's also an MPF failure to pay, which I believe is fairly indicative of a situation where there is a fairly serious financial situation. I mean, all of this is public knowledge, and let me stress, we we have had to rely on public knowledge, public information, things that they have said to the stock exchange.
For example, and again, I would draw your attention to the announcement on the 18th of May, where they failed to pay 300 million US dollars in bond, which triggered a further 150 million US dollars. I mean, there are so many instances that have been indicative of the situation, but the May 18 is the critical one.
If you said,
Now，can you tell me？
Please note number four and number five.
They are verified before they are passed on.
The amount on were substantial.
在2016年晚些時候，即係12個月前。
We annex one the sections that you're referring to.
CDA with a list of subcontractors which they earn money.
what you said, and actually what you meant, in the financial in the finance meeting.
Okay, now if we look at the Annex One, which is the timeline of the event.
That independent contract management seems failed. Would you agree? No, actually, they're doing the job very well.
They are responsible to us to ensure that on a weekly, weekly and monthly basis, all of the funding requests are submitted. They are checked.
Can you speak louder, please? No, they're doing their job very well. Well, then how can HCC have a large sum of money being being debt, not able to pay the subcontractor? If your checking system
是 functioning. Because Annex Two, so you have to speed up. I'm afraid you probably come closer to the mic. Because Annex Two refers to the direct payment arrangements under which we ensured that every payment was properly certified.
WKCDA grow concerned that despite payments made by WKCDA to HCC, which is San Cheng, San Cheng had failed to pay its subcontractors and suppliers in a timely manner. This adversely impacted the progress of the project.
Number five, from November 2016, HCC has been unable to pay its subcontractors from its own resources. HCC approached WKCDA with an objective of rescheduling some of the payments and provided WK.
That's what they do.
You said.
The two are not related.
那 was the reason why.
for the purpose for which it is provided.
但係，issue，they，are，fail，to，misunderstand。Please，correct，me。
If the amount was substantial， okay， how substantial it was。
Well，hang on，it doesn't make sense to me at all，because。
quite quite in order for us to countercheck every claim to make sure that the money is only spent.
Specifically, we decided to accept the request to carry out direct payments.
這係一個最重要嘅方面，係合同管理，而你有個系統或獨立嘅管理、合同管理。
The issue is how quickly does that money get from us to Sinchong? Sinchong to the subcontractors, and that has been the problem. We felt that it was inappropriate to rely on a company that was not paying promptly. Remind, let me remind you.
They failed to pay subcontractors and suppliers in a timely manner. Didn't mean to say they weren't paying them, but they were not paying them promptly. So we felt it was appropriate to step in and make sure those payments were being paid promptly. That was the arrangements. Nothing sinister about it.
哦，我，
and on a weekly monthly basis to ensure all the funding requests are submitted and checked. Okay, if they're all checked and submitted accordingly, then how can HCC have a large sum of money be in debt to the subcontractors? Because of their financial problems, that's exactly why we decided it was appropriate.
Then you shouldn't let them to accumulate to a large big lump sum. If your checking system is appropriate and timely manner. Hang on, the purpose of the checking is to say both to us as the client and Sinchong as the contractor. Yes, the work that is being claimed by your subcontractors is appropriate.
主席。
how much you own?
The Sun Cheong has own.
I don't think I don't think this council allow that.
Why is that? Because of the terms of the contract.
好，咁或者我都畀我哋法律顧問講講。
sorry，that's the that's the fact，perhaps legal adviser can advise。
You perhaps could ask them, but I mean, I can't help you on this one.
Not us. We don't know anything. We don't own anything.
to their subcontractors. I'm simply not able to under the terms of the contract. I'm sorry.
誒唔該，主席，譚議員，你可唔可以講多一次你個問題噉樣嘅？佢而家咧。
Can you advise? Please advise. I mean, like we want to check, you know, how big is the damage? We have no idea.
But you are you are the one to paying them right now, to the subcontractors. Yes, and we paid against certified work done.
係咪？咁之後咧，你睇到第六、第七咧，其實某程度上咧，譬如第六啦，就係話向新商營造分半商直接支付款項啊嘛。
唔知即係即係翻翻去第四嗰點啦，即係第四第五嗰點啦，喺佢嗰個嘅附件一嗰度。咁其實你睇到咧，就係話佢一個好大欠款額龐大啊嘛。
係咪噉佢做好多呢啲嘢嘛？咁而家問緊嘅問題就係話噉你係幾大嘅一個條數？而家講緊譬如你新槍爭幾大嘅錢？呢個唔知唔肯講。第二噉你話唔肯講新槍爭幾大嚿嘅錢？咁第二啦，噉你畀咗幾多錢？即係由你開始。
OK。
嗯。
方面嘅意見啦。
我問。
哇！真係先係。
and the time at the time.
係要留意啦。噉我哋法律顧問都補充下。
嚟到代新窗嚟到畀錢找數，咁嗰條數幾多？你又唔講。
what the question is, I really didn't understand it very well. It didn't seem very clear to me.
Well, first, I'd rather like to hear from Mr Tan.
At November 2016, when you say the amount owed was substantial, I would like to know how substantial it is.
那係，那係一個不同的問題。我可肯定地告訴你，我們已經支付給承包商多少錢。如果那是問題，那不是你的原問題。
呢個兩個問題嚟嘅啊，The two issues here exactly. I can't comment on the first issue.唔係，所以咪第一個咪等翻呢個 adviser 睇下第一個係咪佢完全唔答得，跟住希望第二個再答啦，唔該。
嗱，我我等法律顧問補充咧，因為我知道其實可能佢哋將來都會同新出有啲法律嘅程序，咁所以佢哋係立，咁所以佢哋自己可能即係頭先都提咗，佢哋可能喺個會議上面所講嘅係唔受我哋嘅立法會權力及特權條例嘅保障喺豁免嘅，咁所以佢哋自己。
唔該，主席嗱咁誒，譚議員其實第二個範疇嘅問題咧，我相信剛才西九管理局柏志高先生已經話佢會回應啦。噉我就唔喺呢一度咧做任何嘅補充㗎啦。咁至於就住第一個問題，如果佢哋認為佢哋有一啲嘢係唔能夠講嘅，咁首先佢哋嘅誒資深法律顧問響度啦，佢可以幫到議員。到底佢哋？
認為點解呢一啲問題可能喺我唔知道，可能喺佢哋嘅合約裏邊有啲條款係話佢哋唔講，又或者係佢哋認為呢個可能將會法進入法律程序，噉佢哋唔講咁呢個要首先等佢哋畀咗嗰個基礎我哋先，咁然之後我哋先至可以知道到底要點處理呢個狀況嘅。咁或者睇下西九嘅法律顧問嗰。
the the。
Is it clean enough?
And question one.
There are two separate.
The subcontractors.
which is delivered each month.
好，柏志高先生。
by the contractor to.
streams of information.
that that come one is a a summary.
since we took on the arrangement billion, we're talking large sums here.
How many subcontractors involved? Twenty. Twenty, thank you. Okay.
Can you disclose the amount? If it's not, if you cannot, then why you cannot? And the second question was.
from the contractor, which brings together all of the amounts that are owed.
Mr. Chairman, I'll answer the second question so we can get that out of the way. Okay, we've paid a total of 1.609 billion dollars direct to subcontractors.
subsequently， how much the WKCDA pay directly to the subcontractors？ What is the amount？其實係兩個數字嘅啫。
and。
the contractor.
cost element。
到的 subcontractors。
now the only way that we can.
所以，what happens is that we
the second stream.
adds on the contractors.
is bound to pay his subcontractors.
是the amount which the contractor.
from the amount owed to the contractor.
everything to the contractor and him then issuing separate checks.
That is then certified by the contractor to the contractor administrator.
the the when certified by the contract administrator, that becomes the amount that the authority is bound to pay.
After getting that request, decided that we would issue the separate checks to the subcontractors and deduct the amount of those checks.
know that is if the contractor makes a request to us as the authority to pay the subcontractors directly rather than us paying.
now.
我哋去到新鴻。
The subcontractors.
嗯，It's a.
和The amount owed to the contractor.
They vary from month to month is one reason because they're up and down, constantly, but
所以，那總共付款那去，所以承包商帳户，是總共的總額，的數額，的數額，的數額，的數額。
The management contractor has to carry out for us is to determine how much they're owed from Sinchol.好，就係我理解。That's why I just can't answer that question.
I'm not sure that there's any particular reason why we can't, any particular legal reason why we can't disclose those amounts, because I think.
唔該啊，主席，我想再跟進翻我頭先講緊嗰個，即係佢哋點樣斷定誒新窗營造嗰個啊啊，即係誒誒嘅insolvency嗰個問題。
嗯，新昌集團咧，作為新昌營造嘅母公司咧，誒，剛才我一路都聽到你哋答就話要分得好清楚啦。當然喺法律上對口嘅單位就係新昌營造，呢個啱嘅。
After we had agreed to the request, they gave us the list of subcontractors. We don't know. We still don't know. This is something we may find out now that we directly have an interface with the subcontractors. How much they're owed? In fact, one of the tasks that the new blue poles and the
我見估計，從200萬個月付或付給承包商，降到少於50萬個月，是付給承包商。所以，很難説出在任何時間，究竟有多少欠。
There's no lack of transparency. That's already answered my question. So fifty million to two hundred million is the range. Yeah, basically. I don't think it. I don't think it ever went up to two hundred million. I think I think the the biggest amount we ever paid was around about one hundred and fifty or something around that. Hang on, we need to clarify one point here. Those were the payments.
What we don't know, and I just don't can't give you the answer, is how much they passed on to their subcontractors. That's the that's the challenge we have, because under the contract, that's not for us to know. That's a problem. Well, because because if you look at, so just one more point. Because if you look at number five, you actually said, and Sun Chuen actually.
Actually provides WKCDA a list of subcontractors and which they own money and with the amount as well. That's why I'm asking that should we have a you should have a list to saying you know how much they actually own the subcontractors. That's where's the question coming from? No, that again that that again the issue there was.
有財困有問題。
集團係出現咗好多問題。
呢個好難令公眾接受咯。
the payment was not made.
唔該，主席。Mr. Chairman，我我諗，The point。
噉你都唔去採取行動，結果拖十八個月。
斷到有機會係拖累到新窗營造，都會出現問題㗎嘛。
有一個確定性去明確去確定呢個我明嘅，但係我想同一個實際嘅角度去考慮，就係作為一個。
咁最關鍵咧就係我想向大家指出咧，今日立法會嘅文件畀我哋有個時序表，我想請大家都睇一睇啊，第三二段嗰度。
is very clear from the note 31 and 32, it didn't matter whether we knew whether or not they were the guarantor, because until
但三廿二段就講到好清楚，新昌集團支付唔到呢個債券咧，同新昌營造有咩關係？同佢嘅子公司有咩關係？因為佢嘅子公司係呢張債券票據嘅擔保人啊嘛。
三廿二段講到係乜嘢咧？就係話新昌集團咧本身咧就係因為正正係頭先剛才講二零一八年嘅五月十八號就宣佈佢嗰個公司有個債券佢不能夠支付。
但係我想喺呢一度指出一個觀點咧，就係新昌集團作為佢嘅整體嘅母公司咧，係早喺一兩年前嘅時候，整個一七年，甚至乎去到一八年，甚至乎啊出現嗰個財困嘅情況，要搞到去到揾德勤公司咧去做一個獨立嘅調查報告，亦都發現咗整個新昌集
呢個係佢嘅擔保人，呢件事我諗你哋都好早知喎。你哋你哋又應該唔會唔知㗎。即係如果係有一個噉嘅情況，你知道新昌營造係要幫佢個阿媽嗰間公司係做咗咁多個擔保嘅，呢個新昌集團出現咗財困嘅時候，你係應該判。
呢個唔係二零一八年五月十八號嘅事啊，其實應該係再早啲嘅時候，你哋應該有一個判斷啊嘛。當然你可以繼續同我拗翻頭先嘅觀點，你話誒，我聽到一路都係講一樣嘢，就係話你要判斷到佢係一個所謂資不抵債或者係啊陷入財困嘅情況。當然喺法律上，你係要。
公共機構嘅管理者，如果你係知道呢個新昌集團作為呢間新昌營造嘅母公司，你知道呢間子公司原來不斷咁幫呢間母公司去做擔保，而個阿媽嗰間公司已經一早陷入龐大嘅財困，仲要有份德勤報告指出佢間公司係有。
gentleman, I fail to ask the answer the question because.
determine that fact, and as I said in my opening remarks.
none of them happened, and so it became very clear that.
It's not our job to find a salver salvation for a publicly listed company.
那statement on the eighteenth of May removed any residual doubt that we had. We we already suspected it, but we could not definitively say until that point.
即係如果唔係終止合約啦，你再早啲你又知道佢擔保咗咁多阿媽嗰啲債，喺嗰啲時間你會唔會已經有諗過揾多間公司翻嚟一齊去做咗佢處理呢個問題咧？我就想問問先生。
In other words, another when they failed to pay the debt when it became due, we could not have determined unilaterally that they were insolvent. We were suspecting that was the case. We had written to them to say that we thought it was the case, but we could not.
如果唔係去到嗰個階段，係應該褪翻前，可能半年到一年嘅時間，喺個情況仲有得掹嘅時候，係唔係你冇諗過或者嘗試過揾多間公司翻嚟一齊去做翻一個joint venture去處理呢件事咧？你哋有冇噉樣嘅考慮過咧？
Mr. Chairman, I can say without knowing the contents of the letter, and I'm not going to comment on the contents of the letter. I can say that throughout the period of 18 months, we had at least three different approaches from the company suggesting that there would be a white knight that would come in, throwing money on the table. None of them happened.
until they fail to pay their debt。嗱，好啦，啊，主席，我想追問一樣嘢啫。好啦，嗱，如果頭先柏志高先生同我哋爭辯嘅觀點咧，佢就係話我唔論我就算知道，我就算知道佢係擔保人多，總之我唔一日等到佢畀唔到錢嘅話，我都唔能夠達至到一個結論，話佢係。
所謂資不抵債，但係我想指出個觀點咧，就係第一，如果你一早已經知道佢幫個阿媽間公司做咗咁多擔保，而嗰間集團早係一兩年前已經係陷入財困，你係有所謂你頭先講個字用得好啱啦，你懷疑你suspect係有，你係有懷疑呢樣嘢，但係我都想。
想再指出一點：，如果你有一個噉嘅懷疑，除咗中止同佢之間嘅合約之外，你有冇考慮過？正如喺呢段時間去揾多一間公司去同佢做一個所謂嘅joint venture嘅聯合經營，去起碼可以喺另一種方式去挽救呢個情況咧。因為今日我哋係收到。
呢一封啊新槍畀我哋嘅信裏面咧係提過，當然佢就話喺終止入約之前嘅幾個星期咧，佢哋曾經都有諗過話，提議過可唔可以揾多間公司同佢一做一個drawback嚟解決個問題。當然喺嗰個階段咧，你哋已經有一個結論，呢個未必適合，呢個我都明白。但係我只係想講，如
我唔 sorry， 我哋唔做嗰啲嘢。唔係我哋嘅事，要出面去話畀銀行或者其他公司聽，幫呢間公司，因為佢哋有問題，呢個係佢哋嘅問題，唔係我哋嘅問題。我哋嘅問題係因為佢哋破產，我哋要處理後果。所以唔係，我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我哋唔會做呢啲嘢。我
及過佢喺幾個禮拜，你哋解約之前咧，係畀個一個提議，你哋咧，佢哋係揾咗一間有好即係起碼佢叫做承擔到呢個財政問能力嘅公司，係共同興建呢一個empas，佢完成呢個合約嘅。咁而其實我睇翻個時間。
limited.
啊，等下。
to。
And that was.
subcontract.
啊，陳淑莊副主席。
新鴻Construction。
呃，香港。
sorry，oh that's better。
company，contracting company。
which would then, as a joint venture.
They came to us with a proposal.
until money was on the table, how could we believe anything?
that they would enter into a joint venture agreement with another.
Mr. Chairman, I'll actually defer to Mike on on the issue here because there's a legal issue. But yes, they they've approached us on so many different occasions with different solutions. As I say, none of them transpired. But Mike can perhaps explain the issue about joint venture.
咁誒頭先就話可能有白武士曾經至少三次啦。噉我想問下，咁除咗白武士之外，咁誒新槍有冇曾經確實咁講話誒佢係有一啲合作夥伴可以變成一個聯營噉樣去誒誒做埋嗰個誒M plus嘅project咧？
表上面咧，喺你哋宣佈解約幾個禮拜之前，就即係你哋出嚟答傳媒或者答我哋話：，誒件事其實係檢討緊，係應該誒冇問題可以按正常。其實個時間係你出嚟見傳媒，但係你喺見傳媒裏面都有冇考慮過呢一點嘅咧？其實講嘅時候都。
從一個 legal point of view。
And as it turned out.
成立個原因就係想。
咁但係咧，阿主席我就覺得好神奇咧，就係乜嘢咧？誒，既然呢間公司似乎，
你cannot one company can't make a contract with itself, so that the whole proposal was completely flawed from the
I mean, you. I believe that you are legally qualified, so you would fully understand that you cannot subcontract with yourself.
如果記得嘅話，你就而家答；唔記得嘅話，你後補文件都可以嘅。誒，我諗好基本嘅啫。As I said, they they have um they approached us on a number of occasions with different
Also，from，a，financial，point，of，view，so，I，mean，it's，absolutely，pointless。誒咁誒，我我明白嘅，因為我聽完都係啦。咁但係呢個係咪唯一一次佢曾經話要做一個即係引入一個另外一間公司去做聯營咧？因為頭先講嗰個就唔係JohnVenture啦，即係誒誒HCC就會變成一個subcontractor。
啦，噉佢有冇曾經話真係引入一間公司誒同我一齊做一個即係誒誒聯營，識去完成呢個誒誒Amplus咧？有冇曾經噉樣？你記憶所及咧，因為你冇睇過個信件嘅內容，即係我我我都要公道嘅，因為你之前誒冇聽過，咁所以誒你知或者唔知你就咁誒你。
formulations as to ways that perhaps could solve their financial situation, but let me point out, it can never be for our contractor to suggest that we could subcontract their contract to someone else. It just doesn't work. 我我明白呢個我明白，因為我而家諗緊係有冇辦法佢聯營即係。
主席，噉我繼續講，我繼續問問題。因為咧，如果你睇翻咧八月二十誒誒六誒，即係即係睇翻誒八月誒十七號，即係話誒當西九管理局宣佈中止同新昌營造嘅誒嗰個合約，即係Amplus嗰個合約嘅時候咧，佢就舉咗兩個理由嘅。咁一個咧就係話咧新昌集團咧。
就面臨嚴重財務困難，導致新昌營造頻臨破產。咁呢一個就就呢個，亦都係新昌咧誒營造咧。今日畀我哋嘅其中一封誒，即係個信裏邊嘅其中一個誒誒，佢哋好誒着重嘅地方咧，就係話誒冇公司有問題，並不代表我哋嘅公司，即係佢哋自己。
啲新窗營造有問題嘅，即係個財政有問題嘅。第二咧，誒西九管理局嘅第二個理由終止合約咧，就話新窗營造管理欠佳，導致工程嚴重延誤。咁當然呢一個頭先張愛迪議員都有引述到咧，就新窗營造佢哋自己講嘅一啲誒延誤嘅理由。但係啊，主席我就想逐點。
誒講一講啦，因為頭先咧，當我問呢個blue post嘅時候咧，誒其實法律誒即係誒法律代表咧，即係西藥館呢個法律代表咧，都講到咧，就係話其實呢一個一呢一個咧係純粹就係為咗咧誒誒，即係有機會愛嚟誒no即係誒接手新即係誒amplus嘅呢個原因。
第二咧，誒呢個誒公司咧，亦都係組成得比較急嘅嗱。呢個事實係噉嘅，因為我做咗come search，即係我做咗呢個公司查冊，佢係由誒。如果根據佢嘅説法係正確嘅話咧，其實係由西係由董事局決定拍板到成立咧，係不足一個月嘅嚇。
説話之前，我首先答咗阿陳議員嘅問題啦，主席。
係咪唔使出新聞稿㗎？我哋點會有record啊？
我六月嘅董事局已經決定唔再直接畀分盤商。
居然反而就係阿司徒先生咧，喺十七號跟住嗰日企出嚟搏麥。
講嘅時候就講咗啦，就交代幾多銀碼啦，幾多分判商啦，到今日個分判商數目又唔同咗啦，同埋嗰個誒交代嗰個分判商畀直接嘅分判商銀碼又唔同咗。阿主席，我唔明白咧，點解嗰日阿司徒先生出嚟搏米可以係冇啊？係冇新聞稿，我哋要睇新聞先至知。
即係簡單啲，終止同新槍嘅合約，點解仲要畀十八個月咧？即係仲要代佢哋出十八個月咧？誒，畀呢一個誒分判商咧。第二，我亦都想問下咧，因為根據西九管理局條例，咁當然啦，大家都知道西九管理局係一個法定機構。咁如果佢冇嗰個。
個誒即係嗰個誒法律賦予佢嘅權力嘅話咧，佢就不能越權。咁而家其實你聽咗成個會咧，你就睇得到咧。其實西九管理局咧係代新槍去出糧啊，因為佢見到新槍出唔到糧啊嘛。噉佢係代新槍去出糧，畀啲分撥商。你唔想有苦主，我哋明，但係你有冇？
冇權去咁做咧？呢個係咪一個窿窿照？即係係咪一個誒借貸咧？係咪代係咪畀新槍嘅一個貸款嚟嘅咧？呢個我想搞清楚。第三咧進度嗰度咧，即係喺文件當中，唔好意思啊，主席，我都要指出埋文件當中先講到咧。哇！西九管理局咧，就係柏志高先生咧，成日交代呢個。
M plus咧有幾大進展啊？成我都特登咧去睇下佢哋開完嗰啲董事局會議出嚟交代嗰啲交代啲乜嘢。三月二零一七年開完個董事局出嚟啊，都仲係講緊話M plus工程項目在今年第一季度中錄得誒至今咧最顯著嘅進展噉樣哇，正啊！咁跟住特。
突然之間咧，就去到咧今年六月二十八號咧，即係我嘅理解係當報即係明報啦，開始向西九管理局查詢嘅時候咧，就突然之間開完管理西九管理局之董事局之後，就出現咗一句啦。M Plus工程出現一些延誤，管理局已明確告知總承建商對工程進度的關。
關注即係即係，我覺得呢一樣嘢咧係好唔好唔好自自相矛盾。誒，到最後咧，我亦都想問下政府啦。嚟到呢一刻，其實咧新槍即係嗱，我就覺得好似精神分裂噉嘅西九咧，哇就好似話洞悉先機啊，誒神機妙算啊，咁咧就一路就及住新槍。
咁但係咧，西九管誒誒，但係新窗營造咧，就一直仲可以喺過一段日子投得政府嘅工程。佢而家我嘅理解仲係喺list of contractors嗰度嘅。咁究竟嗱，當然今日冇冇即係發展局嘅代表啦。但係呢個小組咧，主席其實咧係民政事務局同埋發展局聯合。
嘅小組嚟㗎，噉我唔知道即係點解發展局冇代表去到，尤其是今日其實我都覺得幾緊要嘅。而發展局都係錯董事局嘅西九董事局，噉我想了解下睇可唔可以解答到呢啲問題，同埋誒仲有一樣嘢我想問一問咧。其實咧，西九管理局咧喺誒話回覆呢一個誒誒誒誒。
誒嗰個叫做傳媒查詢嘅時候咧，誒分別咧係有兩個嘅新聞稿嘅。第一個新聞稿咧就係七月十六號啊，唔係應該係有分別回應咗兩次。七月十一號啊，七月十六號係第一次回應相關明報嘅報導，但係當時係冇提過。
將我容許我分享一個我自己睇完做完呢啲噉嘅研究之後，我自己嘅睇法啦嚇。
其實咧，誒議員咧，其實好針對一啲嘢咧，就係話喺今年七月同埋八月發生嘅嘢嘅。
其實佢哋係考慮佢一係列嘅措施嘅，包括話可唔可中止合約咧噉。咁但係嗰陣時睇翻咧，其實誒誒睇翻就係話。
內嘅咁亦都未必需要係行到嗰步，因為講真，我諗雙西九誒，我睇即係西九誒做任何決定，佢都諗下佢會唔會畀新窗告翻轉頭㗎嘛？咁所以都保障嘅利益。
好啊！我諗嗱，呢度有兩個涉及啦，一個政府，一個西九。咁但係我唔知道Cherry呢度答唔答到啊？誒，我或者嘗試，其實我都諗住喺會完咗之後，想以一個董事局成員嘅身份講一兩句説話嘅。咁或者我喺誒未講啲翻。
咁為何新窗仍然係喺一個公務工程嘅誒所謂名單之上啦？咁據我哋瞭解咧，誒發展局咧其實係睇緊呢樣嘢嘅嚇。噉我就不便帶發展局回應啦。噉我將你嘅提問轉交畀發展局，等發展局或者書面答你哋啦嚇。咁喺誒一啲重要嘅誒西九管理局嘅。
嘅會議上，逢真係傾跟關於新窗問題咧，咁三個政策局咧，誒都有代表喺度嘅。咁誒容許我講講咧，嗱呢一個呢件事咧係屬於一個contract management合約管理嘅。咁所以嚴格嚟講，西九作為個法人咧，係即係同政府係個角色係有分別嘅。咁所以我哋。
幾位嘅官員喺個鬧喺嗰個西九嘅管理局入邊咧，個身份都係西九嘅管理局成員，確保佢做嘅嘢咧係合理同埋有盡力保障西九嘅利益嘅。咁其實咧誒嗱，大家都知道我上任係四個月松啲啊。咁其實誒，我對住呢個問題咧，其實我曾經考慮過嘢，都同大家有啲。
類同嘅嚇，咁所以我都用我自己嘅時間去睇翻啲file啊，問翻啲同事。咁容許我講一句公道説話，即係誒大家咧都覺得嗯你透明度不足啊，可唔可以早啲講啊？咁其實你而家都中止咗，早知今日何必當初？點解你同佢頂咗十八個月啊？咁成立間blue post有啲乜嘢目的？噉話。
噉，我覺得咧，當呢樣嘢發生嘅時候咧，係正如阿柏志高先生講，係一啲所謂誒一啲誒傳聞嚟嘅喺誒有個誒不具名嘅誒誒資訊啦，同埋喺報紙上咧時不時喺一六年咧都有出現呢啲資料。咁但係因為佢新窗個母公司係一個上。
上市公司，我哋好多時都喺個市場上，喺財經市場上都經常聽好多新聞嘅。咁但係從一個契約嘅問題上，佢哋唔可以無風逐影去有任何行動嘅。咁嗰時西九管理局咧係一啲所謂預防措施，佢嘅預防措施其一咧係包括成立呢個blue post嘅。呢個blue post我睇法咧，其實佢一個。
防火牆，因為你唔知道幾時誒新窗其他嘢，我哋唔可能完全知道。如果佢有一個債權人突然之間做一啲嘢，我哋都要保障西九嘅利益，所以我覺得有個噉嘅公司係一個預防措施。佢呢個西呢個blue post咧，其實佢成立嘅目的咧，主要咧就係愛嚟替佢去管理誒呢一個建築同埋公。
成分判嘅噉，所以可謂係一個令到西九可以進一步出嚟。噉，我覺得除一個預防措施嚟講咧，呢個係一個唔錯嘅一著嚟嘅。咁跟住我其實誒，我因為作為成員，我亦都唔可以有啲嘢太過。我唔知會唔會一啲即係confidentiality一啲機密啦。但係我可以講翻咧，喺如果冇記錯應該係一六年底。
誒未有好確切嘅資料話呢間公司一定唔妥。而第二，大家都知道而家揾一個叫做contract誒management contractor誒項目嘅管理承建商，需時都要六至八個星期。如果中止合約，大家可以估得到對嗰個工程嗰個突然之間個中止嗰個嗰個耗時會更加。
誒，被接納嘅。
嗰間銀行咧，其實我記憶所及咧。
時候，我馬上咧憑記憶，我記得喺三十幾年前咧，曾經有一間銀行倒閉咗嘅。
咗能力合理地保障西九文化區嘅利益咯。好，今日柏治高先生。
誒，因為我都有喺度有户口嘅，所以我時都留意呢個新聞。喺香港嘅時候咧，即係香港嘅金融管理局係話呢間公司喺香港嘅業務係健康嘅，佢都係因為冇公司拖累嘅。
噉我諗，大家咧，其實喺個時序上咧，其實其實有啲議員咧係答嘅問題咧，其實係解決解，我覺得係解答咗另外一議員嘅提問嘅。其實如果大家有睇到咧，喺嗰個時序嘅誒Annex One嘅第九點咧，其實咧誒喺第九點至第十點可以睇得到咧。其實喺一七年嘅。
四月開始咧，其實已經睇得到新窗係有問題嘅。但係喺第十段喺第十個點嘅時候咧，其實佢嘅auditor即係佢嘅誒核數師誒核數師咧，亦都話：喂，其實佢係採取一啲救亡措施嘅。咁所以其實咧，佢嘅救亡措施，我哋唔可以喺咁早已經話喂，你一定唔掂嘅噃噉。
噉我自己覺得喺成個時序入邊咧，其實係由第四十一點咧到到第四十七點咧係好重要嘅，因為呢段時間我亦都可以講就因為期間西九開嘅會咧係我誒基本上咧都全程參與咗嘅。咁可以講咧誒，其實誒係有誒。
誒新窗係曾經講過幾個建議，係佢同幾個合夥人嘅個名，我唔可以講啊嚇。但係西九嘅文件上咧係有對呢幾個合夥人咧係作出一啲分析嘅。我基於我嘅記憶啦，係講咧係佢哋嘅分析係包括呢間公司究竟資產幾多啦，跟即係當然根據佢哋嘅誒查察啦。咁有啲個資產咧係。
其實唔多嘅噉，另外有啲係因為唔喺香港嘅公務工程嗰個表列上邊嘅噉，所以大家覺得呢個咁重要嘅嘅工程係咪誒值得揾一間公司根本就係香港喺公務工程上未承認咧？咁咁以我記得咧記憶所及咧，係有呢啲比較客觀嘅因素，令到覺得佢咧佢嘅建議係唔能夠。
咁另外咧，我亦都覺得咧，誒喺期間咧，誒我哋其實目前嚟講最重要，我覺得係睇翻就唔能夠係話早知今日何必當初，即係將自己放翻喺昔日佢哋有嘅資訊底下睇。噉我自己作為一個遲來嘅參與者，我亦都好坦白講，我認為咧，誒當然。
誒，我哋成日都係講話世事係冇完美嘅，你可以即係enhance可以做得更好，而家回頭睇可以做得更好。但係我覺得喺個時序上咧，係我覺得冇原因去質疑誒西九管理局其實係已經盡能力合理地保障西九嘅利益嘅，即係呢一樣嘢，我作為時來嘅參。
參與者，我可以好坦白講，我覺得係做到呢一點嘅。咁另外咧，我亦都會覺得誒喺期間咧，其實頭頭先阿周浩鼎議員咧，亦都講到話係誒，當然你話即係頭先啊啊陳議員或者其他議員都話，喂有冇考慮到佢其他？因為我哋都冇睇到新窗畀你哋封信啦。咁新窗當然會。
話佢有考慮到其他方案，誒佢哋我哋唔應該終止佢合約啊，或者佢唔覺得佢係誒仲可以誒掙扎求存到嘅。但係正如阿周議員佢都講第十三十二點，佢都係誒佢嘅母公司一個承擔者嚟嘅。噉我以下講嘅嘢咧，我唔知道呢一句嘢係咪一個合係咪合理嘅。但係當頭先阿周議員問嘅。
嚇噉，所以咧，我覺得喺呢一度咧，我哋即係個子公司嘅財政穩健同個母公司個財政是否能夠承擔咧，其實兩者都要一評睇。咁呢一個咧，坦白講，亦都對於西九管理局嚟講咧，係一個唔容易做嘅決定嚟嘅。噉我亦都記得咧，喺其實喺七月到到八月咧，係一個最佳。
It's a.
我哋有冇畀多過？
主席，誒唔該，誒。
好簡單易答嘅潘志高先生。
誒應該要畀嘅錢，呢個第一個問題。
今次個事件發生咧，即係我諗大家都唔想見到啦，因為中間轉contractor一個都幾麻煩嘅事嚟嘅。
the the final point I would I would like to make in response to member is that throughout the period of direct payments
我會just draw members' attention to the fact that up until February of 2017, we were telling this council that we expected completion of the building by the end of 2018.
An obligation on our part to pay for the work that is done. We've not advanced money to the company. We've been paying in accordance with the agreed schedule, and that's very important to state. The second thing, in terms of the delays, in fact.
of this year, that we had concerns over progress on the on the project. Again, I believe that that, from my point of view, is is the most appropriate way for me to convey our concerns to the public because it is an open session.
We have in fact been keeping it under review on on a rolling basis. So every decision to continue that payment was a conscious decision and not one that was automatic. So we've been keeping it very very closely under review throughout, Mr. Chairman. Ah,易志明議員，第一輪。
艱難嘅時間嗰陣時，係我哋開會都開得好密下嘅。咁當然新窗咧係會做一啲誒爭執啦，會畀好多資料。咁但係咧，其實西九管理局咧亦都畀過佢，我唔講唔能夠用話好多次機會，但係好多次嘅討論，其實誒都嘗試過去睇睇嘅，因為大家會知道西九嚟講。
講咧，同埋政府一樣咧，就最重要就係確保個工程係能夠有質素地盡快或者係適時完成嘅。咁所以，我哋對於任何一個舉措會阻誤咗個工程進度咧，其實都好擔心嘅。咁所以其實咧，喺七月八月咧係一個好痛苦嘅時間咧，係因為經過新。
窗係畀好多次嘅資料，大家都覺得係唔係好妥當嘅。咁去到誒真真正正咧，係其實佢幾個畀幾次白冇事嘅建議上嚟咧，都其實睇過係唔係好得。咁大家都覺得咧嗱，當然頭先亦都已經話你點樣判斷係乜嘢時間係乜嘢事件。噉我覺得咧。
大家都要覺得即係做咗十八個月，即係enough is enough。噉我哋都覺得好似似乎錯，即係佢可以揾到一個成功，揾到一個白武士，真係可以合作做咗呢樣嘢，令令到我哋有信心嘅機會好細。噉我諗嗰陣時係經過一個好密集嘅會，係一個唔容易嘅決定。咁大家喺個。
管理局咧係一致支持咗，即係喺個董事局係一致支持咗管理局嘅意見嘅。咁所以我希望大家明白咧，我哋唔可以用即係話所謂早知今日何必當初嘅睇法，係應該睇翻當時喺嗰個時空底下有咩資料，畀佢哋做出一個判斷。噉我都係最重要係話，我重複就係佢係咪盡。
gentlemen, I do need to pick up on a couple of things. First, there's absolutely no question of us giving a loan or in any other way supporting Sinchong throughout this direct payment period, as I've indicated before. Every payment, be it to Sinchong or to the subcontractors, has had to be certified as work carried out. So it's a
In November of two thousand and seventeen, we changed our position very clearly in a paper to the Legislative Council, which stated completion would now be two thousand and nineteen. So we've been as transparent as we could be. I have also been stating, I have also been stating in the open session of the board meeting since February.
噉我有三個問題想請教阿柏志高先生嘅。咁第一個咧就係誒根據文件所講咧，一路你哋誒直接付款畀嗰啲十contractor，然之後再畀佢嘅人誒工人咧，喺呢個過程咧，你哋經過核實，然之後付款嘅。我想問第一個問題咧，誒對公眾嚟講，我。
唔覺得完咗呢個？
爭議解決機制，which is provided for within the contract.
咁噉就係可以誒變成一啲終止合約嘅理由嘅。噉我想問下，而家係咪？
好嘛？呢個我諗要交代嘅。噉啊，另外咧就啊，朱亞迪議員，嗱，因為剩翻時間咧，頭先都畀咗上備分享，咁亦都係好嘅。咁不如我亦都有第二輪想問啊，朱亞迪，你不如問三分鐘好嘛？
第二個問題咧，就睇到文經都講咧，你哋開始有啲交接啦，即係啲新人入場啊，噉樣簽嗰啲合約。噉你哋係咪有信心咧？呢個能夠係好成功、好暢順地過渡，令到呢個Empress個project可以繼續按時間表進行。第三個問題咧，就係當呢啲新人入場嘅。
時間誒可能會牽涉到有一啲成本上嘅變化嘅。噉我唔知道你哋今日有冇呢個數據啦。如果有你可以講，如果冇嘅噉，根據你最失即係你個評估啊，或者到呢個呢個消息有之後，可唔可以盡快係支援我哋立法會咧？咁三個問題。好，我諗三個問題都係好。
Yeah, the first question is is is as I said, we only pay against work done, and that work has to be as part of the direct payment. It has to be first certified by Sinchong itself. It is then checked and recertified independently by the contract administrator.
So we have only been paying for the work that has actually been carried out. And let me stress, we have paid Sin Chong for the work that they've done as well. We have not just paid the subcontractors. So we we we believe that we're we have been paying in accordance with the approved mechanisms. On the second one.
I have to say, and I must pay tribute to the team that's been involved in this. We have moved remarkably quickly to secure a management contractor. Now, let me explain. A management contractor is not the same as a main contractor. I'm sure you're aware of the difference. But for those that are not, the management contractor essentially
manages the contract, but instead of having direct relationship with the subcontractors, we now have that direct relationship, and it means that we will have much tighter control over payments in future. Again, always against certified payments. In terms of the additional costs.
It's actually very difficult at this stage for me to give you those figures for a number of reasons. First, obviously we have the management contractor. Their first job over the next three months is to determine exactly what the costs are likely to be. Secondly, by not continuing our contract with Sinchong and.
Some of the other subcontractors, there are obviously different payment arrangements because Sinchong would have had their costs, their profit, etc. So that comes out of the equation. So there'll be a balancing figure. Honestly, this sort of thing will take months, if not years, to resolve. So I.
我會 like to give you those figures. I just don't have the figures, I'm afraid, so I must apologise. 好，啊，主席，誒，OK，頭兩個問題咧，個答案都係正面嘅嚇。咁第三個咧就你今今日未有啦。咁正如頭先我所講，日後如果當局方或者你哋誒誒西九管理局有呢啲進一步資料咧，就盡快提供啦。
我睇一三分鐘，我哋係O K。唔該，主席。噉就誒，我個問題係因為誒今日都收到誒新窗，即係連續兩日都有信啦。噉就誒反映到其實佢都好似件事喺誒誒，即係佢唔覺得係就咁完咗嘅。噉我想問下，即係唔？
可唔可以係話佢其實係都有可能會挑戰翻呢個終止合約嘅決定咧？噉就誒，因為我睇翻誒呢個西九文化區建築及土木工程嘅一般合約裏面咧，其實關於嗰個終止合約嘅條款，噉我。
睇到有誒七十四點一boy啊，七十四點一doc咧，咁都係誒有提到就話佢如果冇合理解釋之下誒停工超過十四日啦，或者係誒就算作出警告，噉佢都冇盡責去做啊，或者係持續或者嚴重違反合約責任。
誒管理局就認為佢已經係喺頭先嗰兩兩條嘅條款裏面係誒已經係死梗㗎啦，噉就佢就冇辦法，就冇辦法就會用任何方式又翻生，因為如果佢任何方式又翻生去挑戰你呢個終止合約決定咧，咁件事又變咗誒無緣。
嘅喎，因為點解咧？因為之前。
給個，the reasons.
所以之前你冇機會去做過呢個過程。
已經係唔需要向彙報，邊啲係公眾嘅關注咧？
喺八月企出嚟講要同佢哋即係解除合約嘅時候咧，我哋都係嗰日即係。
係咪早啲出嚟向呢個小組報告翻，或者向公眾交代翻咧？件事件係會處理得好啲咧，因為咧，我嘅感覺咧就係。
Mr. Mr. Chairman, the the terms of the contract provide for arbitration, etc. at the completion of the project. So that's why we have to wait until the completion of the project.
嗰個嗰誒主席，我想問下嗰個誒arbitration咧，係咪誒而家管理局係決定即係唔喺佢解約之前去做，而係都諗住係之後先做嘅？潘志高先生。
財政嘅問題，我哋支持嘅決定。咁但係如呢一個處理方式係咪一個合適？即係喂佢同你有合個約，跟住你話喂唔得咯，我覺得你財政唔掂，我要你離場咯。跟住又要即刻要嗰啲人咧係執嘢走咧。
誒雖然咧就話柏治高先生就冇出嚟講到，我話O K就O K噉樣啦，咁但係個做法咧某程度咧都畀人係感覺類似，特別到咧我如果我哋睇翻新窗嗰封信，其中點解仲會好似留咗一條尾巴咁咧？就係當你哋。
How we do that? So we followed the terms of the contract absolutely. But yes, I mean I can't comment on their their letter because I obviously haven't seen it. But I fully expect this will be taken through the dispute resolution mechanism, which includes arbitration, and it could take a long time.
冇啦，就唔係好似頭先譯志明議員即係提問，就話哦係咪可以順利轉去新嘅誒公司嗰度做咧？Patrick Goss先生，Mr. Chairman，as I said earlier，we are in dispute。The company has indicated that to us，so yes，we're inevitably going to end up adopting the
However, I would say that our action is fully in line with the terms of the contract. Specifically, members obviously don't have a copy of the contract, but it is a general contract, seventy three one, which states that if we believe the company is insolvent, we may terminate the employment, which we have done, and seventy four one, which also.
好啊，噉啊，最後我啦，噉我就誒，我咧都好感謝，即係頭先常秘咧，就佢嘅分享，因為雖然佢上任咗四個月，噉佢都追查翻啲文件啦。咁頭先咧，常秘提到咧，喂，我哋嘅關注似乎都係即係集中喺七月八月，即係佢嘅態度嘅變化，可能喺西九管理局上面。咁呢個冇辦法。
冇交代過任何嘅事情，冇上過嚟即係報告過，包括十八個月幫佢頂住咁重要嘅決定係冇交代過嘅。噉我都想問阿常秘嗱，你睇翻曬啲文件啦。咁嗱，我知道即係即係之前係你冇涉及到嘅。咁如果你睇翻即係整件事。
先知道噉，亦都覺得好突然。新窗亦都話佢哋係冇收到你哋嘅通知，你只係同咗一個同事講咗一句噉嘅嘢，跟住就要求佢哋離場。佢哋覺得係好不受尊重，即係我撇除新窗係咪喺嗰個財政上面咧係有問題？咁呢個我哋覺得即係。
咁令到佢肯定係坐住條氣咧，就而家就畀咗幾封信我哋，跟住就話可能同你哋咧喺個合約上面都有爭議。其實係咪有得更好地處理咧？我覺得我都想聽下常備噉，同埋最後尾都問翻柏治高先生，你點樣界定邊啲事件要上翻嚟呢一度嘅彙報，邊啲事？
誒多謝主席啊！你令你畀咗條好難嘅問題，不過我盡量答啦，因為誒即係同主席同埋其他委員都時不時有溝通啦。咁大家喺個互信基礎上，噉我亦都好坦白講我自己意見啦嚇。誒誒，好坦白講，我覺得咧誒，由於新聰係一間上市公司，而對於喺個股票市場。
其實。
天之前唔講咧，我覺得係有合理嘅。
合約啦，在揾一個management contractor嘅時候，佢會唔會可以一個動作係令到立法會議員？
And that's what we did. So we were constrained all the way through. Once the decision is taken that you're going to take over the site, you take it over. So I'm sorry. I would love to be able to do this in a public, and I did it as soon as I could. In fact, holding a press conference immediately.
上咧，經常捕風捉影咧，都可能啲炒作嘅噉，所以我係我覺得咧，因為其實畀立法會嘅資料都係公開資料，所以我覺得我唔會講話有冇一個最好嘅做法或者更好嘅做法。我只會講係咪合理可以諒解嘅做法。我會噉樣睇法。噉我覺得咧，誒喺有件事件，誒有啲蛛絲馬跡喺一六年開。
開始到到今年嘅誒夏天咧，我覺得西九係比較上係三針其口係又合理嘅，因為點解咧？因為管理局咧係唔適宜喺冇實際嘅證據底下就新槍被指被指面對嘅一啲財政困難嘅事咧，係作開一啲公開評論或者畀人種感覺咧，佢已經。
做緊啲嘢咧，係預計新窗唔掂㗎啦噉。因為如果噉樣樣新窗個股價上嘅浮動，或者佢嘅債權人做任何嘅嘢咧，咁唔知道呢間公司會唔會第日誒即係有好多訴訟嘅時候，就指控因為西九做出某啲嘅動作而令到佢哋採取噉嘅自保行為。即係大家會睇得到咧。
如果個我冇記錯咧，呢個誒M家嘅合約咧，係新窗剩翻嘅合約裏邊咧，新窗營造剩翻嘅合約裏邊咧，如果唔係最大都其中一行係最大嘅工程嘅，所以牽涉嘅銀碼多嘅，而佢可以有呢個工程咧，據我理解喺法律上亦都可以當為擁有呢個工程係新窗其中一個asset。
資產嚟嘅噉，所以我覺得咧，佢成立一個blue post，佢唔講咧係理由嘅，係有理由。因為你諗下，如果佢當日一成立個blue post，佢話畀大家聽嘅時候，或者一開始畀錢直接分判商去講嘅時候，大家點問你點解會咁做法？你點解搞咁多花樣咧？咁噉佢咪要將呢樣嘢講出嚟咯？咁所以我覺得咧喺誒今年嘅下。
噉你話啊，今年你應該幾時同我講咧？嗱，坦白講，我有即係我唔可以質疑阿阿Jeremy Stone啊，或者阿阿柏志高先生，或者任何個西九人出嚟面對個傳媒講嘅嘢，係咪大家認為講得最恰當？但係我只會話，可能即係從一個尊重立法會嘅角度嚟講，會唔會係喺佢出新聞稿之？
前少少有封信去畀你哋解釋，咁反正都走出界，即係可能呢一樣嘢會早少少係個尊重。但係你話係咩個時間上係好早話畀你哋聽咧？好坦白講，我覺得係佢一個好睏難嘅決定嚟嘅，因為佢每逢即係畀立法會嘅嘢都會係公開嘅。咁同咗你哋講就等於係從咗。
全香港同傳媒同投資者講兩個説話，咁所以我覺得咧，誒誒，佢一開始做嗰啲自保行為，唔講係有唔公開係有佢理由嘅，係到到就將發覺係冇辦法，一定要改變個處理辦法，要將由誒三十個付款期去翻六十日啦，誒要開始咧係中止呢個。
表感覺到更受尊重，噉我覺得呢個係可以改善嘅空間嘅。咁但係喺個時序上係咪真係褪早好多公開咧？噉我都覺得可可能受益到個空間唔太大嘅，因為畢竟嗰個係上市公司，佢而家仍然係呢間公司。坦白嚟講，仍然係誒誒運作緊㗎嘛嚇。
我按最後，法智好先生有機會嚟解釋埋咧。今日嘅會議議題。This is a couple of things. Um, first, we actually did notify them appropriately because we had our lawyers deliver hand deliver a letter, which we received the timestamp when it was received by the company. There's absolutely no question they received appropriate notice in accordance with.
terms of the contract, so that one I can deal with absolutely. The second one, one of the key issues here is when you seize a site, you don't tell anybody in advance you're going to seize the site. Otherwise, everything disappears, the equipment all goes, all of the goods and services are on site. You go in and you seize it.
sorry。
誒嗰個合約可唔可以提供畀我哋誒參考？就算限月都可以。阿阿譯志明議員唔使唔使擰頭啦，我問下先。我我諗誒限月。
嗰啲都唔緊要，我哋generally我哋都希望睇，尤其是因為有啲point就係誒一睇general就已經可以解答得到，譬譬如話delivery。好，噉啊請秘書處同埋西九嗰度誒會後作出安排啦嘛。好。
while the site was being seized to make it as public as I could, but I couldn't tell anyone in advance. That would have been, frankly, inappropriate. 好，噉我諗啊，我哋今日嘅會議咧就完結啦。不過喺圓會之前咧，我都提翻政府同西九管理局咧。頭先有啲委員提及過關於重新招標可能牽涉到嘅額外支出啊，同埋會。
會啊，即係再有延期啊，同埋今次決定引申到嘅額外支出有關嘅索償等等咧，希望都可以書面回應翻我哋嘅啊小組嘅噉啊，希望可以盡快交到啲資料畀我哋嘅好啊。想額外問一問咧，有冇機會可以將嗰個contract即係誒佢同新窗？
Obviously, as we're in dispute with the company, it would be inappropriate to do so. But I can say, if if members want to look at a general contract, which is the model on which this is based, we can provide a general contract, but not the specifics of this contract.如果冇即係誒general，我哋都想睇一睇，即係至少冇嗰啲咩special conditions。